Finding Aid for the Reverend James M. Lawson, Jr. Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Reverend James M. Lawson, Jr. Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0626
80 linear_feet
Biographical Timeline
1928 Born in Uniontown, PA in
1946 Graduated from Washington High School in Massillon, OH in
1947 Received his local preacher’s license in
September 29, 1947 Entered Baldwin-Wallace College in Berea, OH on
1948 Became involved in the Fellowship for Reconciliation (FOR), which advocated nonviolent resistance to racism in
1951-1952 Declared a conscientious objector, refusing to take either a student or ministerial deferment, and served 14 months in federal prison (two months before graduating from college) for failing to report for the draft during the Korean War
1952 Attended the Hartford Theological Seminary in CT in
December 1952 Graduated from Baldwin-Wallace College with a BA in Sociology in
1953-1955 Worked as a Methodist minister and teacher at Hislop College in Nagpur, India where he studied the principles of nonviolence resistance that Mahatma Gandhi and his followers had developed
1955 Attended Oberlin School of Theology in OH in
1957-1960 Attended Vanderbilt Divinity School in TN in
Served as president of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference for 14 years, the organization founded by Martin Luther King, Jr. to end racial segregation by nonviolent protest
February 1960 Organized sit-ins to stop segregation at lunch counters in downtown Nashville, TN
Expelled from Vanderbilt Divinity School on March 3, 1960, resulting in resignations of faculty members in protest and embroiled the campus and the Nashville community in a nationally reported controversy for months in the spring of 1960. A compromise was forged to stop most of the resignations and allow Lawson to complete dis degree in Nashville. Lawson instead chose to transfer to Boston University.
1960 Founded, along with Martin Luther King, Jr., the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee in
1960 Completed his Bachelor of Divinity degree at Boston University ca.
1960-1962 Pastor at Scott Chapel Methodist Church in Shelbyville, TN from
1961 Coordinated the Freedom Rides in
1962-1974 Pastor at Centenary United Methodist Church in Memphis, TN from
1965 Member of an international peace team in Southeast Asia, replacing Martin Luther King, in
1966 Coordinator of the James Meredith March in Mississippi in
1966 First president of Black Methodists for Church Renewal in
1967 Unsuccessful Campaign for Memphis Board of Education in
1967 Chair of the Strategy Committee for the Memphis Sanitation Strike ca.
April 4, 1968 Martin Luther King, Jr., assassinated in Memphis, TN on
1971 Returned to Vanderbilt on a sabbatical at the Divinity School in
1974-1989 Pastor at Holman United Methodist Church in Los Angeles, CA from
1981 Arrested for praying on the White House grounds in
Chaired Peace Sunday in Los Angeles, CA in 1982, filling the Rose Bowl with 100,000 people
1991 Hosted a weekly call-in show, ‘Lawson Live,’ where he discussed social and human rights issues affecting minority communities ca.
1999 Retired at pastor at Holman United Methodist Church in
2005 Named Vanderbilt’s Distinguished Alumnus in
Lawson’s expulsion from Vanderbilt in 1960 became a source of deep embarrassment to the university. During the 2006 graduation ceremony the university apologized for its treatment of Lawson.
2006-2007 Lawson became a Distinguished University Professor at Vanderbilt for the academic year
The papers contain a wide range of materials documenting Reverend Lawson’s life.
- Education
  - Washington High School
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 28)
    - Photographs (3) (Box 28)
  - Baldwin-Wallace College
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1947 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1948 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1949 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - February 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - May 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - July 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - August 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - September 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - November 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - December 1950 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1951 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1952 (Box 28B)
    - Correspondence - incoming - n.d. (Box 28B)
    - Prayer Notes - 1947 (Box 28B)
    - Sermon Ideas 1947-1949 (Box 28B)
    - Debate Team 1946-1947 (Box 28B)
    - Young People’s Leadership Regional Training Conference 1947-1948 (Box 28B)
    - Newspaper Clippings - 1947-1949 (Box 28B)
    - Pamphlets - ‘The Methodist Church and War and Peace’ 1948 (Box 28B)
    - Classes - Philosophy and Ethics - Spring 1949 (Box 28B)
    - Dean’s List and Scholarship Award 1947-1949 (Box 28B)
    - Worship Services 1948-1950 (Box 28B)
    - Publications 1950-1951 (Box 28B)
    - Methodist Student Loan - 1951 (Box 28B)
    - Methodist Youth Assembly - May 1952 (Box 28B)
    - Will - July 27, 1952 (Box 28B)
    - Commencement - June 7, 1953 (Box 28B)
    - Speech - ‘Alternative to Destruction’ - n.d. (Box 28B)
    - Courses - Education Work of Local Churches – Fall 1956 (Box 29)
    - Courses - New Testament I – Fall 1956 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Courses - Church History Survey – Fall 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - History of Religions – Fall 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - Practicum – Fall 11957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - Psychology of Christian Character – Fall 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - A Year’s Preaching – Fall 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - The Christian Religion – Spring 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - Fundamental of Sermon Construction – Spring 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - New Testament 2 – Spring 1957 (Box 29)
    - Courses - Old Testament History – Spring 1957 (Box 29)
  - Hartford Theological Seminary
  - Oberlin School of Theology
    - Correspondence - Incoming - 1956 (Box 30)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1957 (Box 30)
    - Correspondence - incoming - 1958 (Box 30)
    - Engagement - Fall 1957 (Box 30)
    - International Fellowship of Reconciliation - n.d. (Box 30)
    - Newspaper Clippings - King at Oberlin - February 1957 (Box 30)
    - Newspaper Clippings - 1957-1958 (Box 30)
    - Lexington Conference - 1957-1958 (Box 30)
    - Medical Records - 1957-1958 (Box 30)
    - Methodist Federation of Social Action - 1955-1956 (Box 30)
    - Methodist Youth Foundation - 1956 (Box 30)
    - Minutes - Student-Faculty Meeting - October 11, 1956 (Box 30)
    - Instruction for Colloquy Leaders - n.d. (Box 30)
    - North American Faith and Order Conference - 1957 (Box 30)
    - Programs - 1956-1957 (Box 30)
  - Vanderbilt Divinity School
  - Boston University
- Federal Prison - Conscientious Objector - Korean War
- Church Affiliations
  - Turner Chapel Methodist Church - Canton, Ohio
  - Hislop College - Nagpur, India
  - Warren Chapel Methodist Church 10/1/56
  - Scott Chapel Methodist Church - Shelbyville, Tennessee
  - Centenary United Methodist Church - Memphis, Tennessee
  - Holman United Methodist Church - Los Angeles, California
- Church Committees
  - Ad Hoc Committee for the 1984 Olympic Games
  - Black Methodist for Church Renewal
  - Board of Christian Social Concerns
  - Central Jurisdiction of the Methodist Church
  - Citizens Advisory Committee on Student Integration
  - Citizens Concerned with Improved Police Community Relations
  - Commission on Religion and Race
  - Committee for Nonviolent ACTION
  - Committee of Southern Churchmen
  - General Board of Global Ministries
  - General Conference of the United Methodist Church
  - General Council on Ministries
  - JAPLA: Justice, Action, and Peace in Latin America
  - Joint Task Force on Health and Welfare Ministries
  - National Committee of Black Churchmen
  - National Conference Of Negro Methodists
  - National Council on Churches
  - Quadrennial Emphasis of the United Methodist Church
  - Southern California-Arizona Annual Conference
  - United Methodist Church Renewal
  - Western Jurisdictional Conference
  - World Conference on Religion and Peace
  - World Council of Churches
- Civil Rights
  - General Subject Files
  - Hospital Strike - Memphis
  - Memphis Sanitation Strike
  - Civil Rights Project - see audio-visual
- Assassination
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. - Assassination
  - James Earl Ray
- Organizations
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (FOR)
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC)
- Book Draft
- Return to Vanderbilt University, 2006-2010
- Audio-Visual Materials
  - Cassette Tapes
  - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
  - VHS Tapes
  - Photographs
  - Posters
  - Scrapbooks
- Awards and Plaques